Guide to the Oral History of the American Left Collection OH.002
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series I. Oral History of the American Left Main Series, 1940-2011
  - Abner Berry, 1974-1977; cuid1186
    Berry analyzes at length the relationship between Party policies on race and African American identity. This includes the initial appeal of the Communist Party for African Americans and the organizational implications of the CP policy of black and white unity. He also looks at how this policy fit into larger questions of African American national identity at time, including the CP's relationship with Garvey movement. He also speaks about the study of American history by African American CP leadership and the prevalent desire for assimilation. He also looks at the CP's broader policy towards a mass movement with an American identity, and he analyzes how Franklin Delano Roosevelt's policies and CP policies worked together during the Depression.
    Berry also shares his memories of Party administrators and figures in Harlem. These include Richard Moore, James Ford, Cyril Briggs, Arnold Johnson, Merrill Work, Charles White, and Manning Johnson, who later testified before HUAC. He also shares his recollections of the 1935 Harlem riot and subsequent hearings and Robert Minor's involvement in hearings.
    Also included is an analysis of Richard Wright's work and commentary on the Party, including discussion of Native Son and The Outsider. Berry describes of meetings with Wright, Ralph Ellison, and Theodore Ward, in which they discussed literature, especially the use of symbols. He also describes the CP's attempts to control cultural criticism, and comments on Socialist realism and its divorce from reality. Berry also discusses the Party's acceptance of jazz and folk music, and speaks of the theoretical implications of improvisation in jazz music.
    Berry also discusses the activities of the CP and its interactions with other organizations. This includes his activities and politics in Politburo in the late 1930s; analysis of the trade union caucuses, including Mike Quill and the TWU; the reactions to the Nazi-Soviet Pact; the foundation of the National Negro Congress; experiences working with Garvey movement; and the work of the Ethiopian Defense Committee in Harlem. Berry also describes the Party's working relationships with ministers, including Adam Clayton Powell (Baptist), Johnny Johnson (Episcopalian), Father Phillips (Episcopalian), William Lloyd Imes (Presbyterian), and Father Divine.
    Other topics addressed include the CP education programs for members in Harlem, the high turnover among CP members, differences in debate of African-American self-determination in North and South of United States, the activities of the Workers' Alliance at the Home Relief Bureaus, Unemployed Councils, and interracial marriage in the Party.
    Interview by Mark Naison.
    - Access Copy (Box 12, Cd Berry 1-6)
    - Original Recording (Box 1, Audiocassette 16 A-F)
  - Steve Beumer, Mar 11, 1975; cuid1187
    Interview covers Beumer's family background in Indiana, his political activities there and in Detroit during the late 1960s-1970s, the Socialist Workers Party, and his experiences as bus driver and union activist in Detroit.
    Interview by Claudia Hommel.
    Duration: 219 minutes in three parts
    - Access Copy (Box 12, Cd Beumer 1-4)
    - Original Recording (Box 1, Audiocassette 17 A-C)
  - Martin Birnbaum, Nov 6, 1977; cuid1188
    Interview documents the life and activities of a Yiddish "proletarian poet" including his childhood, immigration and literary work for New Yorker Volkszeitung during the 1920s, his friendship with writer Moshe Nadir, the role of the Left in the Yiddish literary community, the Proletpen circle of writers, Birnbaum's disillusionment with Communism and poetic realism, and his return to unrestrained lyricism.
    Duration: 96 minutes in two parts
    - Access Copy (Box 12, Cd Birnbaum 1-2)
    - Original Recording (Box 1, Audiocassette 18 A-B)
  - Martin Birnbaum, Feb 5, 1978; cuid1189
    Duration: 58 minutes
    - Access Copy (Box 12, Cd Birnbaum 3)
    - Original Recording (Box 1, Audiocassette 18 C)
  - Martin Birnbaum, Feb 16, 1983; cuid1190
    Interview covers the meaning of the "sense of humor" in Yiddish literary work and Birnbaum's own sense of humor contrasted with that of writer Moshe Nadir and Jewish popular culture.
    Duration: 17 minutes
    - Access Copy (Box 12, Cd Birnbaum 4)
    - Original Recording (Box 1, Audiocassette 19)
  - Violet Wainio Bjong, Jul 7, 1984; cuid1191
    Interview covers the activities of Wainio Bjong's father and mother, Finnish-American radical leaders during the 1920s-1930s, her activities in Fitchburg, Massachusetts during the 1930s, work on a Left-oriented daily in Fitchburg, life in Brooklyn cooperative housing, and reflections.
    Duration: 65 minutes
    - Access Copy (Box 12, Cd Bjong 1)
    - Original Recording (Box 79, Audiocassette 265)
  - Fred Blair, Jul 26, 1983; cuid1192
    Interview covers the role of ethnicity in Communist Party of Wisconsin during the 1930s-1940s; support of the Left from the Polish sector dating back to 1880 and support of other Slav groups from 1910s; role of Meta Berger in Wisconsin Party and Blair's ascendency to state leadership; unemployment demonstration in Milwaukee and influence on students in University of Wisconsin-Madison; increase of District membership with addition of northern Wisconsin; character of northern Wisconsin rural Communists; exodus of rural Communists from state during the 1940s-1950s, and the impact of McCarthyism on the decline of Communist Party support.
    - Access Copy (Box 12, Cd Blair 1)
    - Original Recording (Box 1, Audiocassette 20)
    - Transcript (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Norman Bloomfield, May 7, 1983; cuid1193
    Interview topics include the Young People's Socialist League during the 1930s; Trotskyism; the University of California, Berkeley campus; and work in shipyards.
    - Access Copy (Box 12, Cd Bloomfield 1)
    - Original Recording (Box 1, Audiocassette 21)
  - Grace Lee Boggs, Mar 28, 1983; cuid1194
    The interview includes a discussion of Boggs' Asian-American family background in Providence, Rhode Island; her education and involvement in radical politics in New York during the late 1930s; the Workers Party and Johnson-Forest tendency during the 1940s; Correspondence in Detroit during the 1950s; involvement in the Black Power movement with her husband, James Boggs; and comments on C.L.R. James.
    - Access Copy (Box 12, Cd G. Boggs 1-2)
    - Original Recording (Box 1, Audiocassette 22-22 A)
  - Grace Lee Boggs, Aug 6, 1986; cuid1195
    Topics discussed include entry into radical politics, the Johnson-Forest Tendency, and the relationship of culture and the Left.
    Interview by Ellen Kellman.
    - Access Copy (Box 12, Cd G. Boggs 3-4)
    - Original Recording (Box 10, Audiocassette 420 A-B)
  - James Boggs, Mar 29, 1983; cuid1196
    Interview covers Boggs' youth in the South, factory life in Detroit during the 1930s-1940s, the Johnson-Forest Tendency, and activities in 1960s-1970s.
    - Access Copy (Box 12, Cd J. Boggs 1)
    - Original Recording (Box 1, Audiocassette 22)
    - Original Recording (Box 1, Audiocassette 177 C)
  - James Boggs, Aug 6, 1986; cuid1197
    Interview regarding Boggs' involvement in the Johnson-Forest Tendency.
    - Access Copy (Box 12, Cd J. Boggs 2-3)
    - Original Recording (Box 10, Audiocassette 421 A-B)
  - Paul Booth, Oct 1969; cuid1198
    Interview discusses Students for a Democratic Society, its internal politics, relationships with other student groups, and demonstrations.
    Interview by Kirkpatrick Sale.
    - Access Copy (Box 12, Cd Booth 1-2)
    - Original Recording (Box 10, Audiocassette 422)
  - Frank Bohn, Mar 1, 1958; cuid1199
    Interview includes Bohn's memories of Elizabeth Gurley Flynn, Thomas Hagerty, the Catholic church, and the Socialist Labor Party.
    - Access Copy (Box 12, Cd Bohn 1)
    - Original Recording (Box 1, Audiocassette 24)
  - Fannie Borun, Jan 6, 1981; cuid1200
    Political struggles within the International Ladies Garment Workers Union during the 1920s, experiences on trips in the Soviet Union during the 1930s, and women's role in the Communist Party.
    Interview by Bea Lemisch.
    Duration: 63 minutes
    - Access Copy (Box 12, Cd Borun 1)
    - Original Recording (Box 1, Audiocassette 25)
  - Judy Boudon, Feb 7-8, 1982; cuid1201
    Interview includes discussion of Boudon's immigration from Panama, the Spanish-language immigrant community in New York during the 1930s, her work in offices and factories, the America Labor Party, the Communist Party, and women's role in the CP.
    - Access Copy (Box 12, Cd Boudon 1-2)
    - Original Recording (Box 1, Audiocassette 26 A-B)
    - Transcript (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Thomas Brandon, Nov 4, 1976; cuid1202
    Interview covers the Workers' Newsreel and Film and Photo League during the early 1930s.
    Interview by Russell Campbell.
    Duration: 85 minutes; Preservation note: Muffled sound/low volume
    - Access Copy (Box 12, Cd Brandon 1-2)
    - Original Recording (Box 1, Audiocassette 27)
    - Original Recording (Box 10, Audiocassette 27)
  - Miriam Braverman, Nov 8, 1984; cuid1203
    - Access Copy (Box 12, Cd Braverman 1)
    - Original Recording (Box 81, Audiocassette 364)
  - Jeremy Brecher, Mar 31, 1970; cuid1204
    Brecher discusses the activities of the Students for a Democratic Society between 1962 and 1965.
    - Access Copy (Box 12, Cd Brecher 1-2)
    - Original Recording (Box 1, Audiocassette 28)
  - George Breitman, Jan 4, 1979; cuid1205
    Interview covers the activities of unemployed organizations in New Jersey and the Socialist Workers Party between 1938 and 1954.
    - Access Copy (Box 12, Cd Breitman 1-3)
    - Original Recording (Box 1, Audiocassette 29 A-C)
  - Harry Brier, Aug 26, 1983; cuid1206
    Brier discusses life in the East End of London during the 1920s-1930s, the Jewish character of Communism, anti-fascist activities in London during the 1920-1930s, his immigration to Los Angeles, and union activities, from the 1940s to the time of the interview.
    - Access Copy (Box 12, Cd Brier 1)
    - Original Recording (Box 1, Audiocassette 30)
  - Theodore Brise, Apr 18, 1980; cuid1207
    Interview contains discussion of anarchism and Arbeter Ring in Los Angeles, Yiddish anarchist activists, and the Rudolf Rocker Circle.
    Duration: 45 minutes
    - Access Copy (Box 13, Cd Brise 1)
    - Original Recording (Box 1, Audiocassette 31)
  - Brookwood Labor College, Oct 10, 1982; cuid1208
    Recording of a slide show on the history of Brookwood Labor College and Workers' Education Local 189, with comments by former Brookwood staff and students.
    Narrated by Jon Bloom.
    - Access Copy (Box 13, Cd Brookwood 1-4)
    - Original Recording (Box 1, Audiocassette 32 A-D)
  - Niki Brorsen, May 20, 1975; cuid1209
    Interview contains discussion of Brorsen's family background and growing up in San Francisco and Chicago during the 1950s-1960s, the anti-war work, and Brorsen's decision to join the Young Socialist Alliance during the late 1960s. It also addresses her work as a waitress and activities in restaurant union during the 1970s.
    Duration: 119 minutes in two parts
    - Access Copy (Box 13, Cd Brorsen 1-2)
    - Original Recording (Box 1, Audiocassette 33 A-B)
  - Peter Buch -- Transcript, Aug 24, 1976; cuid1210 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    Interview documents Buch's immigration from Turkey and youth in Los Angeles, brief involvement in Socialist Zionism during the early 1950s, the Socialist Workers Party and Young Socialist Alliance in Los Angeles and nationally during the 1950s-1960s, the Robert Williams case, responses to Cuban Revolution, and the Vietnam War.
    Interview by Douglas Cooper.
  - Heinz Buergers, Apr 26, 1980; cuid1211
    Interview by Beth Haskell.
    - Access Copy (Box 13)
    - Original Transcript (Box 2, Audiocassette 39)
  - David Burbank, Oct 6, 1984; cuid1212
    Interview contains discussion of Saint Louis radicalism during the 1930s, the Socialist Party, the American Workers Party, the Trotskyist movement, and the Workers Party. Also discussed is CLR James in Missouri and unionization of gas workers.
    - Access Copy (Box 13, Cd Burbank 1)
    - Original Recording (Box 1, Audiocassette 35)
  - Ann Burlak-Timpson, 1977; cuid1214
    This talk covers labor activities in Rhode Island during the early 1930s and her role as a Communist speaker, and organizer in Providence and Pawtucket.
    Public address, Rhode Island Labor History Forum.
    Duration: 20 minutes; Preservation note: Audio quality is very poor.
    - Access Copy (Box 13, Cd Burlak-Timpson 6)
    - Original Recording (Box 2, Audiocassette 36)
  - Ann Burlak-Timpson, Dec 18, 1980; cuid1213
    Interview covers Burlak Timpson's labor activities in Rhode Island and Communist activities during the 1930s-1940s.
    Duration: 257 minutes in five parts
    - Access Copy (Box 2, Audiocassette 35.1 A-E)
    - Original Recording (Box 13, Audiocassette Burlak-Timpson 1-5)
  - C., Pete, undated; cuid1215
    This interview with a Detroit-based socialist, includes a description of his background, the appeal of socialism, and his involvement with the Teamsters.
    Interview by Sam Friedman.
    - Access Copy (Box 13, Cd Pete C. 1-2)
    - Original Recording (Box 10, Audiocassette 427 A-B)
    - Transcript (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - James P. Cannon, undated; cuid1216
    Recording of speech titled "What Socialist America Will Look Like."
    - Access Copy (Box 13, Cd Cannon 1)
    - Original Recording (Box 10, Audiocassette 413)
    - Transcript (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Fanny and Herman Cantor, Jan 11, 1979; cuid1217
    Interview covers immigration to US from Russia and development of social consciousness, growing up in Hell's Kitchen in New York, radicalism and cooperativism during the 1920s-1930s, and reflections on younger radicals and current events at the time of the interview.
    Interview by Milton Cantor.
    - Access Copy (Box 13, Cd Cantor 1)
    - Original Recording (Box 2, Audiocassette 37)
  - Philip Caplowitz, Nov 15, 1980; cuid1218
    Interview covers Caplowitz's immigration, the activities of Jewish Communists in unions during the 1920s-1930s, and Yiddish culture and the Yiddishe Kultur Farband during the 1930s-1980s.
    Duration: 77 minutes in two parts
    - Access Copy (Box 13, Cd Caplowitz 1-2)
    - Original Recording (Box 2, Audiocassette 38 A-B)
  - Wendell Carroll, Nov 30, 1983; cuid1219
    Interview covers the activities of American Youth for Democracy during the late 1940s, the Independent Socialist League during the early 1950s, ISL positions on the Korean War, the Rosenberg case, the Communist Party and McCarthyism, and race and civil rights.
    Duration: 104 minutes in two parts
    - Access Copy (Box 13, Cd Carroll 1-2)
    - Original Recording (Box 2, Audiocassette 39 A-B)
    - Transcript (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Pincus Caruso, Mar 16, 1983; cuid1220
    Interview covers the origins of Labor (Paole) Zionism in Eastern Europe and Caruso's role in the early 20th century; the formation and publication Yiddishe Kempfer in New York; the growth of Poale Zionism during the World War I era and brief publication of daily Zionist newspaper; growth of Zionism in the 1930s-1940s and support of Israel; and reflections on the failure of Zionists regarding Arabs in Israel and the conservative Israeli leadership.
    Duration: 88 minutes in two parts
    - Access Copy (Box 13, Cd Caruso 1-2)
    - Original Recording (Box 2, Audiocassette 40 A-B)
    - Transcript (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Catholic Worker Conference, May 2, 1983; cuid1221
    Program held at Trinity College in Worcester, Massachusetts to honor Dorothy Day and founding of the Catholic Worker. Includes panel comments by John Cort and others regarding Day and the Catholic Worker.
    - Access Copy (Box 13, Cd Catholic Worker Conference 1-2)
    - Original Recording (Box 2, Audiocassette 41 A-B)
  - Reverend Don Chase, Nov 5, 1983; cuid1222
    Interview documents activities against the United States' intervention in Nicaragua in 1928, Christian Socialism in a San Francisco parish during the 1930s-50s, and Chase's interpretation of the Liberation Theology of the 1970s-80s.
    - Access Copy (Box 13, Cd Chase 1-2)
    - Original Recording (Box 2, Audiocassette 44 A-B)
  - Bernard Chazanow, April 26, 1977; cuid1223
    Interview documents Chazanow's role as a political activist in Russia from 1898-1909 and the activities of the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union (ILGWU) from 1909-1928.
    Duration: 54 minutes
    - Access Copy (Box 13, Cd Chazanow 1)
    - Original Recording (Box 2, Audiocassette 42)
  - Bernard Chazanow, May 31, 1978; cuid1224
    This recording contains an interview to supplement Chazanow's 1956 Yiddish autobiography, Days and Years.
    Preservation Note: Incubation was attempted on these audiocassettes, however they could not be digitized due to their condition.
    - Access Copy (Box 13, Cd Chazanow 2-4)
    - Original Recording (Box 2, Audiocassette 43 A-C)
    - Transcript (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Rose Chernin, Oct 25, 1983; cuid1225
    Interview documents the origins and activities of the Los Angeles branch of the Committee for the Protection of the Foreign Born during the 1940s-1950s, Chernin's family life, and her relationship with her daughter.
    - Access Copy (Box 1, Cd Chernin 1)
    - Original Recording (Box 2, Audiocassette 45)
    - Transcript (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Harold Christoffel -- Transcript, Jun 27, 1974; cuid1226 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    Interview documents the early union background of former president of United Auto Workers Local 248 Allis Chalmers in Milwaukee, Wisconsin during the 1930s.
    Interview by Roger Keeran.
  - Helen Ciminelli, Joe Richter, and Ann David, Oct 26, 1982; cuid1227
    Interview covers the activities of SNPJ (Slovenska Narodna Podporna Jednota), a Slovenian mutual aid society, in Fontana, California, during the 1930s-1980s and the SNPJ role in Henry Wallace presidential campaign.
    - Access Copy (Box 13, Cd Ciminelli, Richter, David 1)
    - Original Recording (Box 2, Audiocassette 47)
  - Alice Citron, Jan 6, 1981; cuid1228
    Interview documents Citron's career as a teacher in Harlem during the 1930s-1940s, her involvement in the Teachers' Union, her dismissal during the McCarthy era, and struggle for reinstatement.
    - Access Copy (Box 13, Cd Citron 1)
    - Original Recording (Box 2, Audiocassette 48)
  - City College of New York Memorial, Apr 13, 1980; cuid1229
    Recording of a dedication of a memorial for thirteen CCNY alumni members of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade killed in action in the Spanish Civil War. Includes speeches from ALB vets and historians, a recording of a speech by Ernest Hemingway, and musical performances. Speakers include Robert Colodny, Philip Foner, Joseph P. Lash,
    - Access Copy (Box 13, Cd City College 1-2)
    - Original Recording (Box 2, Audiocassette 46 A-B)
  - Egidio Clemente, May 11, 1981; cuid1230
    Clemente discusses his role as editor of La Parola and secretary of Italian Socialist Federation in the 1930s, Italian left factions in Chicago and other cities, and the left wing Italian presses.
    Interview by Eugene Miller.
    - Access Copy (Box 13, Cd Clemente 1)
    - Original Recording (Box 2, Audiocassette 50)
    - Transcript (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Lucy Ann Cloud -- Transcript, Aug 25, 1972; cuid1231 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    Interview covers the Industrial Workers of the World and Centralia, Washington case of 1919, with particular reference to IWW attorney Elmer Smith.
    Interview by Tom Copeland.
  - Charles Coe, Dec 5, 1991 - Jan 9, 1992; cuid1232
    Interview by Emily Raphael.
    - Access Copy (Box 14, Cd Coe 1-2)
    - Original Recording (Box 80, Audiocassette 315 A-B)
  - Nat Cohen, Nov 5, 1977; cuid1233
    Discussion of disconnect between Communist Party leadership and working class society. Analysis includes discussion of relationship between leadership and rank and file members; the Party's inability to speak to the broader society's cultural interests; sports; the missed opportunity to engage with Communist movements in communities outside of New York, Chicago, and Los Angeles; and the relationship between art and the Party line.
    - Access Copy (Box 14, Cd N. Cohen 1)
    - Original Recording (Box 10, Audiocassette 392)
  - Rose Cohen -- Transcript, Apr 12, 1976; cuid1234 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    Recollections of studies at the Jefferson School of Social Science.
  - Joseph Cohen, Ruth Cohen, and Frieda Koren, Jun 9, 1983; cuid1235
    Interview regarding "Carlo" (Jesse Cohen), a cartoonist of the Workers Party during the 1940s.
    Duration: 19 minutes
    - Access Copy (Box 14, Cd Cohen and Koren 1)
    - Original Recording (Box 2, Audiocassette 51)
  - Julia Conroy, May 14, 1980; cuid1236
    Interview by Theresa Diamond.
    Duration: 39 minutes
    - Access Copy (Box 14, Cd Conroy 1)
    - Original Recording (Box 2, Audiocassette 53)
  - Olga Corey, Jan 18, 1983; cuid1237
    Olga Corey, the daughter of Louis Fraina (Lewis Corey), discusses her reaction to the movie Reds, reminiscences of father at Antioch College during the 1940s, and her own union activities.
    Duration: 42 minutes
    - Access Copy (Box 14, Cd Corey 1)
    - Original Recording (Box 2, Audiocassette 54)
  - Carlos Cortez, Jul 25, 1983; cuid1238
    Cortez discusses being the son of a Mexican-American activist who joined Industrial Workers of the World after San Diego Free Speech Fight, his father's life in Milwaukee during the 1920s, and his mother, a German-American Socialist and poet. Cortez also discusses his imprisonment during World War II as conscientious objector, the role of the IWW in Chicago Mexican-American community during the 1940s, his role as artist and speaker for IWW in the 1940s-1980s, and anarchism and the IWW.
    Duration: 71 minutes
    - Access Copy (Box 14, Cd Cortez 1-2)
    - Original Recording (Box 2, Audiocassette 55 A-B)
    - Transcript (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Carl Cowl, Mar 13, 1983; cuid1239
    Duration: 96 minutes
    - Access Copy (Box 14, Cd Cowl 1-2)
    - Original Recording (Box 2, Audiocassette 57)
  - Malcolm Cowley, Jan 19, 1981; cuid1240
    Interview covers the Left during the Great Depression, the League of Professional Groups, "Culture and the Crisis" in 1932, the proletarian novel, John Reed Clubs, the Communist Party's Popular Front strategy, the Spanish Civil War, and reflections.
    Interview by Richard Wormser.
    - Access Copy (Box 14, Cd Cowley 1-2)
    - Original Recording (Box 2, Audiocassette 56)
    - Transcript (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Roy Curtis, Nov 4, 1984; cuid1241
    Interview with Roy Curtis of the International Association of Theatrical Stage Employees (IATSE) Local 4.
    Interview by Paul Richiuso.
    - Access Copy (Box 14, Cd Curtis 1-3)
    - Original Recording (Box 80, Audiocassette 308A-B)
  - Joseph Cvetas, Oct 22, 1982; cuid1242
    Cvetas discusses his family's background with the Slovenian fraternal society SNPJ (Slovenska Narodna Podporna Jednota), participating in the fraternal society's activities as child, and fraternalism in 1980s.
    - Access Copy (Box 14, Cd Cvetas 1)
    - Original Recording (Box 2, Audiocassette 58)
  - Sam Darcy, 1981; cuid1243
    Interview includes a discussion of Darcy's immigrant background, Communist activities during the 1920s, factionalism, Browderism, his departure from the CP, subsequent activities, and reflections.
    - Access Copy (Box 14, Cd Darcy 1-3)
    - Original Recording (Box 2, Audiocassette 59 A-B)
  - Sam Darcy, Nov 3, 1994; cuid1244